Ted Hughes papers, 1940-1999
Emory University
- Writings by Ted Hughes, circa 1949-1990, Series 2; Boxes 57-86; OP2-58a; 105-107; OBV1
  - Prose, Subseries 2.4; Boxes 87-115; OP42-58a
    - Book-length prose, 1967-1995, Subseries 2.4b; Box 87: folder 4 - Box 112: folder 3; OP43-45
      As with much of Ted Hughes's work, Shakespeare and the Goddess of Complete Being (SGCB) went through an exhaustive drafting process. Its beginnings were in the introduction he wrote in 1971 for his selection of Shakespeare's verse, and indeed TH included in the SGCB archive some initial rewrites of his Essential Shakespeare introduction. "[T]his rewrite eventually developed – through these manuscripts" (TH's index note, Box 21) into a series of letters Hughes wrote to Donya Feuer from 23 April to 14 June 1990. In a note attached to the archive, TH writes that "Danya Feuers [sic] works with Ingmar Bergman in the Swedish Royal Dramatic Theatre in Stockholm. She is an old friend who has done a great deal of work with Shakespeare – a great deal of work, toe [sic], in developing my ideas about the plays with Swedish actors." As he notes in the "Foreword" to SGCB, "it [occurred] to me that if I anatomized what I had identified as Shakespeare's myth, as it revealed itself in each work, and followed through what are to me its fascinating evolutions, and set it all out in letters to Donya Feuer, bit by bit, as simply as possible, who knows, maybe something would emerge. Those letters became this book" (xiii). In the letters to Feuer, Hughes has already divided his project into five broad sections. Thereafter he begins to divide up these sections into smaller "chapters," as many as 80 of them, eventually arranged into six sections (instead of the initial five – see 24 July 1991 letter to his copy editor, Gillian Bate), and then further arranged into three very broad "Parts." In a letter of 30 July 1991, Bate recommended that he remove the small numbered chapters and instead refer to the six sections as chapters, still under three broad Parts. This is the general final structure of the published version. There are seven complete typescript drafts of SGCB in the collection. For purposes of differentiation, they are numbered TS 1 – 7 according to their apparent order of composition.
      Arranged by date of publication.
      - Poetry in the Making (1967, 1969; US version called Poetry Is, pub. 1970)
      - "Capturing Animals," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 4)
      - "Introduction" [See also Subseries 2.6: Children's Writing, Shaggy and Spotty] (Box 87, Folder 5)
      - "Learning to Think," TS draft (Box 87, Folder 6)
      - "Meet my Folks," TS draft (Box 87, Folder 7)
      - "Moon Creature," TS draft (Box 87, Folder 8)
      - "Wind and Weather," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 9)
      - "Words and Experience" (epilogue), MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 10)
      - "Writing a Novel: Beginning," TS draft (Box 87, Folder 11)
      - "Writing a Novel: Going on," TS draft (Box 87, Folder 12)
      - "Writing about Landscape," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 13)
      - "Writing about People," TS draft. (Box 87, Folder 14)
      - Appendices and misc. poems, MS and TS (Box 87, Folder 15)
      - Poetry in the Making: Draft of title page and table of contents (Box 87, Folder 16)
      - Poetry in the Making: Galley proof (Box 87, Folder 17)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971, 1991)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 18)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 19)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 87, Folder 20)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 88, Folder 1)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1971): Complete draft of volume (Box 88, Folder 2)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts [mostly on salmon paper] (Box 88, Folder 3)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 88, Folder 4)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 88, Folder 5)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse(1991): "Introduction," MS and TS drafts (Box 88, Folder 6)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," various TS drafts (Box 88, Folder 7)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," marked "Final" and dated 18 February 1991, TS (Box 89, Folder 1)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," TS, and some verse selections (Box 89, Folder 2)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): "Introduction," TS, annotated by Craig Raine (Box 89, Folder 3)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): Corrected Faber proofs, pp. 1 - 100 (Box 89, Folder 4)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): Corrected Faber proofs, pp. 101 - end (Box 89, Folder 5)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): Faber galley proofs (Box 89, Folder 6)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse (1991): Faber galley proofs (Box 89, Folder 7)
      - The Essential Shakespeare: Corrected TS [sent with letter of 2 July 1991 from Cathy Jewell (Ecco Press) to TH] (Box 89, Folder 8)
      - The Essential Shakespeare: Corrected galley proof [sent with letter of 30 August 1991 from Jewell to TH] (Box 90, Folder 1)
      - The Essential Shakespeare: Corrected galley proof of "Introduction" [sent with letter of 4 October 1991 from Jewell to TH] (Box 90, Folder 2)
      - The Essential Shakespeare: Related correspondence, particularly between Jewell and TH [17 letters]; includes a 23-page letter of explanation and corrections from TH to Jewell, TS (Box 90, Folder 3)
      - A Dancer to God (1992)
      - Various MSS and some TS drafts of T. S. Eliot: A Tribute [published 1987 [A93], eventually became chapter one of ADTG] (1) (Box 90, Folder 4)
      - Various MSS and some TS drafts of T. S. Eliot: A Tribute (2) (Box 90, Folder 5)
      - Various MSS and some TS drafts of T. S. Eliot: A Tribute (3) (Box 90, Folder 6)
      - "A Dancer to God," TS. (This TS has title replaced with "The Poetic Self," the title for essay's republication in Winter Pollen) [See also Subseries 2.4: Essays, Reviews, Talks, "Unidentified (response to James Wood review talking about T.S. Eliot and anti-semitism)"] (Box 90, Folder 7)
      - "The Truly Great," for unveiling of T. S. Eliot's blue plaque on 26 September 1986, MS and TS drafts (Box 90, Folder 8)
      - "Notes" section, TS and MS [ MS is a longer version which discusses the Arvon foundation and TH's critique of English Literature as an academic discipline] (Box 90, Folder 9)
      - Corrected proofs (Box 90, Folder 10)
      - Shakespeare and the Goddess of Complete Being (1992, 1993)
      - MS and TS drafts of "King Lear" letter to Donya Feuer (Box 91, Folder 1)
      - Diagrams (Box 91, Folder 3)
      - "Notes to Shakespeare sequence" (Box 91, Folder 4)
      - MS and TS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (1) (Box 91, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (2) (Box 91, Folder 6)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (3) (Box 91, Folder 7)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (4) (Box 91, Folder 8)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (5) (Box 91, Folder 9)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (6) (Box 91, Folder 10)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (7) (Box 91, Folder 11)
      - MS drafts of letters to Donya Feuer (Hughes #20) (8) (Box 91, Folder 12)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 1)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 2)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 3)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 4)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 5)
      - Early MSS Drafts (Box 92, Folder 6)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 92, Folder 7)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 1)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 2)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 3)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 4)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 93, Folder 6)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 1)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 2)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 3)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 4)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 94, Folder 6)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 1)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 2)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 3)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 4)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 95, Folder 6)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 1)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 2)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 3)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 4)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 6)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 7)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 96, Folder 8)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 1)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 2)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 3)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 4)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 5)
      - MS drafts of SGCB, including drafts of letters to Feuer (Box 97, Folder 6)
      - MS draft of SGCB [Foreword and Introduction] (Box 97, Folder 7)
      - MS draft of SGCB [Section 1] (Box 97, Folder 8)
      - MS draft of SGCB [Sections 2-11] (Box 97, Folder 9)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Section 12] (Box 98, Folder 1)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Sections 14-24] (Box 98, Folder 2)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Section 25] (Box 98, Folder 3)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Sections 26-30] (Box 98, Folder 4)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Sections 31-40] (Box 98, Folder 5)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Sections 41-50] (Box 98, Folder 6)
      - MS and TS drafts of SGCB [Sections 51-58] (Box 98, Folder 7)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section I, 23 - 26 April, TS (Box 99, Folder 1)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section I, 27 April - 3 May, TS (Box 99, Folder 2)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section II, 4 - 11 May, TS (Box 99, Folder 3)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section II, 12 - 17 May, TS (Box 99, Folder 4)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section III, 18 May - 26 May, TS (Box 99, Folder 5)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section III, 27 May - 2 June, TS (Box 99, Folder 6)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section IV [3 - 6 June 1990], TS (Box 99, Folder 7)
      - Letters to Donya Feuer: Section V [8 - 14 June 1990], TS (Box 99, Folder 8)
      - Proofs marked with pencil by Craig and Li Raine (Box 100, Folder 1)
      - TS 1: Complete TS (Foreword, Introduction, Sections 1-15 of 58) (Box 100, Folder 2)
      - TS 1: Complete TS (Sections 17-40 of 58) (Box 100, Folder 3)
      - TS 1: Complete TS (Sections 41-58 of 58) (Box 100, Folder 4)
      - TS 2: Complete TS (Sections A-R of 59) (Box 100, Folder 5)
      - TS 2: Complete TS (Sections 1-11 of 59) (Box 100, Folder 6)
      - TS 2: Complete TS (Sections 14-30 of 59) (Box 101, Folder 1)
      - TS 2: Complete TS (Sections 31-48 of 59) (Box 101, Folder 2)
      - TS 2: Complete TS (Sections 49-58 plus postscript and appendices of 59) (Box 101, Folder 3)
      - TS 3: Complete TS, 1 of 5 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 101, Folder 4)
      - TS 3: Complete TS, 2 of 5 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 101, Folder 5)
      - TS 3: Complete TS, 3 of 5 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 101, Folder 6)
      - TS 3: Complete TS, 4 of 5 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 101, Folder 7)
      - TS 3: Complete TS, 5 of 5 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 102, Folder 1)
      - TS 4: Complete TS, 1 of 4 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 102, Folder 2)
      - TS 4: Complete TS, 2 of 4 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 102, Folder 3)
      - TS 4: Complete TS, 3 of 4 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 102, Folder 4)
      - TS 4: Complete TS, 4 of 4 (59 chapters, appendices, postscript) (Box 102, Folder 5)
      - TS 5: Complete TS, 1 of 4 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 675pp) [letter to Julie Armstrong inserted] (Box 102, Folder 6)
      - TS 5: Complete TS, 2 of 4 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 675pp) [letter to Julie Armstrong inserted] (Box 103, Folder 1)
      - TS 5: Complete TS, 3 of 4 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 675pp) [letter to Julie Armstrong inserted] (Box 103, Folder 2)
      - TS 5: Complete TS, 4 of 4 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 675pp) [letter to Julie Armstrong inserted] (Box 103, Folder 3)
      - TS 6, pp. 3-149 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 4)
      - TS 6, pp. 150-300 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 5)
      - TS 6, pp. 301-450 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 6)
      - TS 6, pp. 451-601 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 7)
      - TS 6, pp. 602-684 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 8)
      - TS 7: Complete TS, pp. 1-75 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 9)
      - TS 7: Complete TS, pp. 76-200 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 103, Folder 10)
      - TS 7: Complete TS, pp. 201-449 (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 104, Folder 1)
      - TS 7: Complete TS, pp. 450-Notes (80 chapters, appendices, postscript, 684pp) (Box 104, Folder 2)
      - Appendix Three [Merchant of Venice; for revised UK and US edition], TS (Box 104, Folder 3)
      - MS and TS notes for "Introduction" and resources (Box 104, Folder 4)
      - "Introduction," corrected TS (Box 104, Folder 5)
      - "Letter to the Reader" and "Letter to the Editor," MS and TS (Box 104, Folder 6)
      - "Acknowledgements," TS (Box 104, Folder 7)
      - Inserts and Corrections (Box 104, Folder 8)
      - Lightly Corrected TS of Chapters, notes, and appendix (Box 104, Folder 9)
      - Lightly Corrected TS of Chapters (Box 104, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous TS (Box 104, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous TS (Box 105, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous TS (Box 105, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous TS (Box 105, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous TS (Box 105, Folder 4)
      - SGCB Galley proofs, incomplete (Box 105, Folder 5)
      - SGCB Galley proof, Faber and Faber (I) (Box OP43)
      - SGCB Galley proof, Faber and Faber (II) (Box OP44)
      - SGCB Faber uncorrected advance proofs, bound in light blue cover (Box 105, Folder 6)
      - SGCB correspondence, principally between TH and Gillian Bate, SGCB's copy editor [34 letters]. Includes some correspondence between TH and Christopher Reid (Faber) (Box 105, Folder 7)
      - SGCB correspondence: correspondence between TH and Richard Proudfoot (Box 106, Folder 1)
      - SGCB correspondence: correspondents include Craig Raine, Keith Sagar, Olwyn Hughes, and Moelwyn Merchant (Box 106, Folder 2)
      - Replies to critical reviews of SGCB: includes prose responses to Eric Griffiths and John Carey (Box 106, Folder 3)
      - Notes by TH on arrangement of chapters (Box 106, Folder 4)
      - "A Brief Guide to SGCB," TS drafts [in the form of a letter to "Michael"] and a brown notebook of MS notes (Box 106, Folder 5)
      - SGCB artwork (Box 106, Folder 6)
      - Faber cover designs and sketch by TS of potential cover design (Box 106, Folder 7)
      - "Blurb" for SGCB, TS (Box 106, Folder 8)
      - Winter Pollen: Occasional Prose, ed. William Scammell (1994)
      - "Author's Preface" by TH and draft of contents for a proposed earlier selection of TH's prose by Ekbert Faas; plus various MS notes for the preface and contents (Box 106, Folder 9)
      - Incomplete series of chapters from Faas prose selection, TS, with initial contents page annotated in blue pen (Box 106, Folder 10)
      - Incomplete series of chapters from Faas prose selection, TS, with chapter numbers pencilled in top right hand corner (Box 106, Folder 11)
      - "Burnt Fox," corrected final TS (Box 106, Folder 12)
      - "Crow on the Beach" and letters from which essay was conceived, MS and TS (Box 106, Folder 13)
      - "Fantastic Happenings and Gory Adventures," MS and TS (Box 106, Folder 14)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS (Box 107, Folder 1)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS and TS; copious versos (Box 107, Folder 2)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS and TS; copious versos (Box 107, Folder 3)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS and TS (Box 107, Folder 4)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS and TS; copious versos (Box 107, Folder 5)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," MS and TS; copious versos (Box 107, Folder 6)
      - "The Hanged Man and the Dragonfly," final TS versions (Box 107, Folder 7)
      - "Inner Music," TS drafts (Box 107, Folder 8)
      - "Keats on the Difference between the Dreamer and the Poet," TS (Box 107, Folder 9)
      - "Myth and Education," annotated TSS (Box 108, Folder 1)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," MS and TS (Box 108, Folder 2)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," MS and TS (Box 108, Folder 3)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," MS and TS (Box 108, Folder 4)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," MS and TS (Box 108, Folder 5)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," MS and TS, with MS notebook pages of notes for essay (Box 108, Folder 6)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," TS corrections with TH note "Rough" (Box 108, Folder 7)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," corrected TS (Box 108, Folder 8)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," heavily corrected TSS (Box 108, Folder 9)
      - "Myths, metres, rhymes," TS with TH note "FINAL" (Box 108, Folder 10)
      - "Poetry and Violence," MS and TS drafts (Box 109, Folder 1)
      - "Poetry and Violence," corrected TS (Box 109, Folder 2)
      - "Publishing Sylvia Plath," corrected TS (Box 109, Folder 3)
      - "Shakespeare and Occult Neoplatonism," annotated photostat (Box 109, Folder 4)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," pink notebook with MS notes (Box 109, Folder 5)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," MS and TS drafts (Box 109, Folder 6)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," MS and TS drafts (Box 109, Folder 7)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," TS draft [marked "Final"] [See also Subseries 2.3 "Miss Dinsdale," MS [comic poem for the Queen Mother] and Subseries 2.6: Difficulties of a Bridegroom, "Deadfall"] (Box 109, Folder 8)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," TS draft [copy of "Final" with further annotations] (Box 109, Folder 9)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," TS postscript (Box 109, Folder 10)
      - "The Snake in the Oak," related correspondence and corrections (Box 109, Folder 11)
      - "Sylvia Plath's Collected Poems and The Bell Jar" [only in US edition], MS and TS (Box 109, Folder 12)
      - "Vasko Popa," MS notes (Box 110, Folder 1)
      - "A Word about Writing in Schools" (Box 110, Folder 2)
      - Winter Pollen, various TS corrections (Box 110, Folder 3)
      - Winter Pollen, corrected complete TS (Box 110, Folder 4)
      - Winter Pollen, corrected complete TS [1 of 3] (Box 110, Folder 5)
      - Winter Pollen, corrected complete TS [2 of 3] (Box 110, Folder 6)
      - Winter Pollen, corrected complete TS [3 of 3] (Box 110, Folder 7)
      - Winter Pollen, "first proof," corrected (1 of 2) (Box 110, Folder 8)
      - Winter Pollen, "first proof," corrected (2 of 2) (Box 111, Folder 1)
      - Winter Pollen, "second corrected proof" (Box 111, Folder 2)
      - Winter Pollen, proof with very few corrections (Box 111, Folder 3)
      - Winter Pollen, corrected pages for paperback edition (Box 111, Folder 4)
      - Winter Pollen, miscellaneous materials [including list of queries from copy editor; TH note for editor; list of Winter Pollen sources; correspondence with editor] (Box 111, Folder 5)
      - Difficulties of a Bridegroom, 1995
      - "The Deadfall," MS (Box 111, Folder 6)
      - "The Deadfall," TS (Box 111, Folder 7)
      - "The Head," MS (Box 111, Folder 8)
      - "The Head," MS (Box 111, Folder 9)
      - "The Head," TS (Box 111, Folder 10)
      - "The Head", Corrected TS (Box 111, Folder 11)
      - "The Wound," MS and TS drafts [See Subseries 2.5, The Wound] (Box -, Folder -)
      - Difficulties of a Bridegroom, Acknowledgements [See Subseries 2.3: Crow, "Crow was aware of another at war"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - Difficulties of a Bridegroom, Proof with corrections (Box 112, Folder 2)
      - Difficulties of a Bridegroom, Proof (2nd) with corrections (Box 112, Folder 3)
      - Difficulties of a Bridegroom, Proof with corrections (Box OP45)
    - Introductions and forewords, 1962-1997, Subseries 2.4c; Box 112: folder 4 - Box 113: folder 10; OP46
      The subseries consists of manuscript and typescript drafts of introductions and forewords written by Ted Hughes from 1962-1997. Because of Hughes' propensity to reuse paper, cross-references are used to note locations of related materials in other parts of the collection.
      - An Anthology of Poetry for Shakespeare, edited by Charles Osborne, 1988, MS and annotated TS (Box 112, Folder 4)
      - Ballad of King Henry VIII and Sir Thomas Wyatt by Priscilla Napier, 1994, MS (Box 112, Folder 5)
      - By Heart: 101 Poems to Remember, "Memorising Poems," 1997, MS (Box 112, Folder 6)
      - Children as Writers 2, 1975; republished in Winter Pollen as "Concealed Energies," MS and TS (Box 112, Folder 7)
      - A Choice of Coleridge's Verse, 1996, preface, MS and TS [with sketch of snake-like animal in black ink] (Box 112, Folder 8)
      - A Choice of Coleridge's Verse, 1996, corrected proofs (1) (Box 112, Folder 9)
      - A Choice of Coleridge's Verse, 1996, corrected proofs (2) (Box 112, Folder 10)
      - A Choice of Emily Dickinson's Verse, 1968, MS and TS drafts and associated correspondence (Box 112, Folder 11)
      - A Choice of Emily Dickinson's Verse, 1968, proof w/o corrections (Box 112, Folder 12)
      - A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse, 1971, 1991 [See Subseries 2.4b: A Choice of Shakespeare's Verse] (Box -, Folder -)
      - The Essential Shakespeare, 1991[See Subseries 2.4b: A Choice of Shakespeare's Vers e] (Box -, Folder -)
      - First and Always: Poems for Great Ormond St Hospital, 1988, TS draft (Box 112, Folder 13)
      - Five American Poets [with Thom Gunn], 1963 [B19] (Box 112, Folder 14)
      - Here Today, 1963, Galley proof with corrections by TH (Missing Introduction by Ted Hughes) (Box 112, Folder 15)